[Music]
hello and welcome to episode 10 of the
inventory tutorial series in this video
we're going to rework how the items are
stored in memory and how we save them
out so by the end of the video
not much will have changed
in the editor
i'll be able to you know go over here
and put stuff into the chest just as we
always have been able to
and we can hit save but now as kind of
pointed out at the end of the last video
if i built and run this version of the
game i wouldn't be able to load that
save in the built version of the game
originally but by the end of this video
we will be able to do that so you can
see here we're in the built version of
the game and we can now hit load and the
save files are in sync between the
actual built version of the game and the
editor version as well we'll be able to
go over here you know make some changes
go into this chest put this thing here
put some tomatoes in the player's
backpack we can hit save we can go back
into the editor hit play and our save
files will be in sync
so you see there's our tomatoes and each
of the chests has what we put in it
we'll be creating a database that
controls all of our items and assigns
the items and id as well so let's just
get started with a video okay so let's
get started let's go over to our item
scripts folder right-click create
c-sharp script and we'll call this
database and let's open up that in our
ide so this is going to derive from
scriptable object so we'll get rid of
start and update and we'll place
monobehaviour with scriptable object
now we're going to need to be able to
right click and create a database in the
project so let's do create asset menu
and we can say menu name is equal to
inventory
system
slash uh
item
database
let's just zoom in a bit
so we've got our database object here
um so the first thing i want to do is
serialize field a private list
of inventory item data so these are the
other scriptable objects that we have
and i'm just going to call this the
item
database
also since starting this project
many many months ago i've upgraded kind
of my naming conventions to fit more in
with
how c-sharp should be coded so you'll
notice that here i've got privates
without an underscore
and you can see rider is complaining
saying it should have an underscore
so it doesn't really matter but
that's why my name in conventions have
changed so i'm putting underscores on
under private variables just so you're
aware
so this is going to be a list this is
our database this is the list of all of
the items in our game
and this is kind of like the one sort of
point of truth
so when we load in a game we can look
for an id instead of the instance id
which as i said last time can change
between builds and the editor and
patches and updates like it's not very
safe
this way we can assign an id to a item
say like one two three
and then our save file can say that
we've saved item three and item three
will always be item three it won't
change in between
it won't change in between sessions and
it will go between the
and the editor and the build will share
the same item database so we'll be able
to load our save games that we've made
in the editor in a built version of the
game
and would be able to
load the save file that's in a built
version again back up in the editor
which would be great for debugging and
stuff like that
so with that said so with that little
bit more of an explanation either way um
we're gonna make a function
to actually set these ids so i'm going
to do a public void set item
ids
and i'm going to above that give it the
context menu attribute with the set id's
name
so we can call this in the inspector if
we need to
so the first thing i'm going to do when
we set some item ids is i'm going to
create a new
list of inventory item datas this will
just ensure that the database is never
null when we start to try and do stuff
with it
and the first thing i want to do is i'm
going to make a variable called found
items and i'm going to search the
resources folder by calling resources
load all
and i'm going to get it to
load all of the inventory item data that
we have in our project
and this is going to be at the path of
item data
and then i'm going to use
system.link so let's come up here we'll
do using system
dot
link
and we're gonna order all of our items
by their id
so if
say apples is an id of so if tomatoes is
an id of one and potatoes are an id of
two
it will put them into the order so it'll
put tomatoes first and then potatoes so
we can do order by and the way the order
by function works is quite easy so we
need a letter or a variable name because
this is almost like doing a for reach
loop so we're saying for each i or this
can be anything this could be for each
um
for each item
but convention is to just have one
letter so ordered by i so for item
for each item let's order it by the item
dot id
and then finally let's put this
into
a list called found items so again we're
loading all of our item data scriptable
objects that we've created they're going
to be in a folder called item data
and then we're going to
saw all of those inventory items we're
going to order them by their id and then
we're going to put them into a list
called found items and now we need to
filter these found items into three
separate categories
we need to say um
has id in range that's going to be one
of the categories
we're going to
has
no
an id
not in range
i'll explain these all in a second
um and
we want no id as well
so here we're seeing whether say we
found
10 items
but for some reason
uh
tomatoes had an id of five but then
potatoes had an idea of 15.
the one that has an id of five would be
in range because it's in the range of
the amount of items that we found
the ones that had an idea of 15 or
anything above how many found items we
had
they would have a valid id but it
wouldn't be in range
and then no idea are going to be all new
items that we've never set an id for
before
and we're going to default them and when
we make a new
inventory item data we're going to make
it so it always defaults to -1 which is
what we can then check for
so let's focus on has id and range first
so i'm going to set this variable equal
to found items so we're going to check
this list
and we're going to get all the ones
where
our
item
id
is not equal
to minus one
and
the item's id
is less than the found items dot count
and then we're going to order that list
by their id so
just the same as above and then we're
going to put them all into a list
and this seems quite complex
in terms of you know memory usage it
might not be the most efficient but this
is only going to get called when we
build the game this is never going to
happen
uh like in game where there's a player
doing this
so for our purposes as long as it's
functional
i'm more than happy with that going into
a built version of the game so for the
not in range we're going to do the exact
same thing but we're going to change the
um
check on the count so we can say
equals found items where their id is not
equal to -1
and the id is greater than or equal to
the found items.count and then we'll put
that into
an ordered list
and then finally
we're going to copy our found items
where i'm going to say where the item id
is less than or equal to -1
and we'll put that into a list as well
so now we're going to loop over all of
our lists and organize them into the
item database in the correct order
the ones that don't have an id we're
going to give an id
and because they're scriptable objects
this id will then be persistent that
data will stay
we don't need to save it out to a list
like to a json list or anything like
that
so i'm going to make a temporary index
um variable just called index and we'll
set that to zero
and i'm going to go into a for loop i'm
going to say for int i
and while i is less than the found items
dot count so all of the items in our
game
i plus plus and i'm gonna make a new um
inventory item data called item to add
because depending on some
different checks this is going to decide
what item that is that we're checking
and then we'll put this item into the
list
so here we're just checking the id
at i i'm going to check the found
items.range and we'll see if the item
that we're looking at has the same
id
as the position that it's come through
into the ordered list so
we're going to say item to add is equal
to has id in range
dot find
and i'm going to say
where the
data
and i'm using d here instead of i
because we've already got i here i'm
going to say where the data is equal to
the data's id
equaling i
sorry that's not equal it needs to be
that so
so when we've got to this index that
we're on
we're going to assign it a work we're
going to sign an item from this list
this has id and range list
so we're going to get the id that
matches the current iteration of the
loop that we're in
if
the item to add is not null at this
point then
then we are good we can add that item to
the database because that's
the correct item in the correct position
so
item to
add can go into the database
if the
item to add is null so we've not found
an item that's within the range that
we're looking for doesn't have a correct
id
then we're going to check does the index
which is this variable
here that we've made
is the index less than the id
is less than the no id
dot count
so this is a separate index that we're
keeping track of over here because we're
going to iterate this when we run this
bit of code
to make sure that we don't go out of
range of this no id list so if there's
no id what we're going to do is we're
going to
get the
item that is at the index
that we're looking at i'm going to set
its id equal to
i
and again i is the current like loop
index
so essentially we're going to get the
first time around if we get to here
we're going to go into this list of no
ids and we're going to get item 0 and
we're going to set it to the relevant id
of this loop
and then we can say item to add is equal
to no id
dot index
we will increase the index so this is
the sort of internal index to this no id
list so we're going to increase the
index and then we can add
the item to add to our item database so
item
item to add goes into the database
and then once this has ran and we've
gone completely through this loop
all we're going to do then is we're
going to go through
all of the items
that
have an id but the on in range
so we'll say for each item in has id not
in range we're just going to add them to
the end of the list so item.database
dot add
item
so this will be a case of say you had 15
swords in your game and you decided
that's too many
i'm gonna take out five but you're only
going to take out kind of like the
middle five and then the last sword
which was originally the 15th sword and
had an idea of 15.
players have that testers have that you
don't want to remove that id from the
database
because it might be referenced in a save
file somewhere
doing this ensures that those ids don't
have to change they can still be valid
and if you add more items into the
future it's going to fit it into kind of
the next available slot in our list
so that's the set id method complete
so now all we need is a
method that returns some inventory item
data
and we can call this get item
and we can just pass in an id
and all this is going to do is return
the item database dot find
and it's going to find the
item
that has the id
that we've just passed in so
find the item where the item.id is equal
to
i
d
which is this id here
because once we run this item ids
because it's a scriptable object
the item database will just stay around
until we call set item ids again
so we don't need to run this at runtime
we can just run this the once when we
build the game or while we're testing
the game in the editor then that's all
we need that's
that's all we need to do
so let's save our database
and let's just go back to our project so
now you need to make a folder called
resources so i'm going to create
a folder
and let's call this
resources i'm actually going to put this
into our item scripts because you can
have multiple resources folders
so remember we were looking in a folder
called item
data
i'm going to put all of our
scriptable objects so the potato and the
tomato i'm going to put this into
our item data folder
and in the root of our resources folder
i'm going to create
inventory system
item database and i'll just call this
database so whatever you name this is
what you're going to refer to it as in
some code later so
um
make sure you name it appropriately
called item database database um i'm
just gonna leave it as database so you
can see here that our list of items is
empty
we've got our item data here and their
id is currently set to
zero let's just set these to minus one
and let's actually open up our inventory
item data
and i'm gonna set this equal to minus
one so when we create a new inventory
item it will be automatically set to
one so let's do inventory
inventory item
and i'll call this
apple so you can see id is set to -1
and we'll just type in apple here
um so if we go back to our database
um
so i'm gonna set the potato
so these are all minus one so if we go
to our
database
and we come up to the three dots here
you can see that it's got set ids and
this is what we did with that context
menu if we hit that
you can see that it found all of the
items in the item data folder it found
three items
it found apple first
so this is id 0
id 1 is the potato id 2 is the tomato
and that matches element 0 element 1
element 2 from the database list
if
for example this was set to
this one was 0
we'll put this one back to -1
and i'll put this at
50.
so it's going to find all of the items
but it's going to put them into their id
order so this is id 0 so it'll go into
element 0 in the list
and then it'll find this one has minus 1
and element 1 doesn't have a matching id
so it's a basically a free
so it's basically an id that is free to
be assigned to another item so we'll set
apple to one
and it'll leave id as for the tomato as
50 and it'll just put it at the end of
the list so let's go back to our
database
and let's just set the database back to
zero
so if i click set ids
so you can see element zero is the
potato
which had an id of zero it set the apple
to id of one
and tomato has been left at an id of 50.
so if i create another
inventory item and i'll call this
pair
we'll do display name pair and i'll
leave the id for now at -1
so what we would need to do now is we
need to
load
our items back into the game based on
their id not their instance id
so let's go back over into our ide
and we're actually going to go over to
the inventory slot dot cs file
and here we're going to implement the
i serialization callback receiver
which is an interface that allows us to
get a call back when the game
when the game is being serialized so we
can get a call back so just before it's
serialized so then after it's serialized
and we'll
implement um the missing members
which are these two scripts here which
are these two methods here's public void
on before serialize public void on after
uh deserialize
and we don't care about on before
serialized we don't need to use that but
so we have to keep it around though so
i'm going to get rid of the throw
exception the method that we're going to
use is on after d serialize
but first we need to go back up and we
need to assign an inventory id to our
slot so serialize field
private
int
and we'll call this
item id and we'll default this to
negative one
so when we save out our inventory system
and all of the inventory slots we're not
actually going to be saving out the
items contained within the slot anymore
we're just going to be saving out this
int which was the
which will correspond to an item in the
item database
so this can be private but it has to be
serialized with serialized field
one so we can see an inspector and two
so it saves out into our json save data
so let's go back to on after d serialize
so here i'm gonna check uh whether the
item
id is equal to -1
if it is the slot's empty so we don't
need to get the item data
and instead what we can do is i'm going
to make a temporary variable called
database and i'm going to set this equal
to resources.load
i'm going to
load the database from our resources
folder
and it's going to be called
database
because it's in the it's called database
and it's in the root of our resources
folder
what you may want to do is get this
what you may want to do is load this um
database into memory on your game
manager or on some sort of singleton
somewhere just so you can always access
it you're not having to load it each
time the game deserializes
but for the purposes of this this is
fine and then all we're going to do is
say item
data
is equal to the database dot get item
and we'll pass in
our item id
so now let's go up to the assign item
method here so this is when we pick up
an item
and we're assigning an item to the slot
what we want to say is um
so the data is equal to the data and our
item id is equal to the item data's
id
which is the id that was set for to it
by the database
in um clear slot we just want to set the
item id
back to negative one
because the slot will be empty
and when we create a
slot in the constructor
we just want to set the item id to the
id
there as well
and we just want to put
item id into the update inventory slot
as well
so that should be that let's go back
over to unity and just check that that's
all working so let's hit play
let's pick up some tomatoes and potatoes
go over to the player and you can see
here that we've got the tomato and it's
got an item id of 50. i've got the
potato item id of zero
and then the slots that are empty have
an item id of minus one so i'm going to
delete my old save file because again
we've done some structural changes to
the way stuff is saved and i'm actually
going to hit save here
and let's load up that save data
so here you can see that item data
instance id is still being saved out we
don't need it to
in fact it's confusing that it is so
let's just mark that as non-serialized
so in our inventory slot
instead of serialized field
we can do
um
non-serialized
but you can see that the rest of it
we've got the item id and the stack size
so it's loading it in
by item id and
not by the item data's instance id
so this will never change this could
change
so let's just check that again let's
delete our save let's pick up some stuff
let's put it in a chest over here
and we'll hit save
let's check that save
so here we've got our chest inventory
and you can see that it's just saving
out the item id and the stack size it's
not got any of the instance id stuff now
so we've saved that let's come back out
of the game go back in
let's hit load game
so there's our potatoes everything
deleted off the floor
we've got our chest which is where we
put the tomatoes originally
i'm just going to split that stack put
it over here
put them in there so i'm going to save
the game and let's just check that it
all works in the build version of the
game as well
so i'm going to come over to our
database
and make sure we set the ids
if you want to see how you can automate
this and get the database to set
when you hit build click the little icon
in the top of the video now
i covered that a couple of days ago
i covered that in a previous video just
follow through with that and you should
be able to see how i got the database to
save when i hit build
it will search for and add all the items
to the database that i may have forgot
to put in myself
and you can see that if we've hit build
and run we're in the game we hit load
and now our save files
uh kind of in sync between the actual
player
and the editor and you can see that
there's our tomatoes
got these tomatoes here
let's put potato in
come on that let's save our game again
i'll afford to quit we can press play
here
hit load
and the save files are now in sync which
is great for debugging so later on as
your game progresses and you start to
get beta testers if they say i've got
this weird bug with my game they can now
send you to save files you'll be able to
load it up in the editor and start to
debug what exactly is going on
so i hope that was useful for you i'm
glad i caught that bug and thanks again
to the commenter for letting me know
about it for the future of this
inventory tutorial series i'm currently
prototyping a shopkeeper system so
you'll be able to sell items at a shop
to make some gold
that's currently in the prototyping
phase it depends when this video comes
out and how far i've got with that and
what else has gone in life when that
will be
but subscribe if that is something that
you'd like to see if you want the
project files for this tutorial or any
of the other tutorials on my
channel you can get them over on
patreon.com there's a link for that in
the description below if you need any
help with this tutorial or any of my
tutorials you can come over to the
discord again which is linked in the
description below but in the meantime
thanks for watching and i'll see you in
the next one bye
you